Guide to the Susan Watkins papers, 1964-2016
Watkins, Susan papers,
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Susan Watkins papers, 1964-2016
23-19-4278
Susan M., Watkins, 1943-
2 Cubic Feet.
Correspondence, course material, memorabilia, and published material.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Includes correspondence, course material, awards, and publications documenting her founding of the academic field of functional apparel design and her career at Cornell.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Watkins earned a B.S. in consumer services and business in 1965 and an M.S. in textiles and clothing in1967 both from Pennsylvania State University. In 1967 she was hired in the Department of Textiles and Apparel at Cornell University as an assistant professor, becoming a professor emeritus in 1999. She founded the academic field of functional apparel design and in 1991 was inducted as a Fellow into the International Textile and Apparel Association.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Includes correspondence, course material, awards, and publications documenting her founding of the academic field of functional apparel design and her career at Cornell.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Watkins, Susan M., 1943-; Cornell University -- Faculty.; New York State College of Human Ecology. Department of Textiles and Apparel.
Subjects:
Fashion design.; Protective clothing.; Clothing industry -- Study and teaching.; Textiles and Apparel -- Study and teaching.; Fashion design.; Protective clothing.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
CONTAINER LIST
- Narrative written by Watkins describing in detail her career and the items donated to the archives (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Description of textiles and clothing programs at Pennsylvania State University and Cornell, 1965-1969 (Box 1, Folder 1A)
- Exams and course outline, 1964-1967; Pennsylvania State University (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Thesis in Clothing and Textiles, 1967; Sassaman, Susan; Pennsylvania State University (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Cornell appointment letter, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Course TC 141 outline and handouts, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Course TC 215 outlines and handouts, 1968-1969 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Course plan for flat pattern design, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Revising the curriculum text, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Course TC 151/DEA 145 outlines and handouts, 1968-1969 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Course TC 151/DEA 145 exams, Undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Course TC 151/DEA 145 station exam, Undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Course TC 151/DEA 145 final projects, course evaluation, Undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Course DEA 145 notes, memos, exams, 1970--1971 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Description of course TC 044/DEA 144, Undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Course TC 044/DEA 144, course proposal, 1969-1974 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Course TC 044/DEA 144 exam, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Course DEA 044 lesson plans, auto-tutorial examples, 1969-1970 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Course TXA 300 outline, exams, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Teaching by television text, Undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
- 1967 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Speech "Preconditioning for Television Learning" and course outlines, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Research on use of television, 1969-1971 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Description of course TC 152/DEA 146, Undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Course TC 152 outlines, 1969-1970 (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Course TC 152 photos of dress forms, Undated (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Description of the move to DEA, Undated (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Notes on speech, Undated; Kennedy, Stephen (Box 1, Folder 27)
  Chief of Textile, Clothing and Footwear Division of Quartermaster Research and Development Center
- Course DEA 345 outlines, 1971-1972 (Box 1, Folder 28)
- Ice Hockey Study, Undated (Box 1, Folder 29)
- Women's holster project, 1977-1978 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  First course devoted to functional clothing design
- Description of course DEA 445/TXA 445, Undated (Box 1, Folder 31)
- Course DEA 445 outlines and statements, 1973-1985 (Box 1, Folder 32)
- Course DEA 445 reading lists (Box 1, Folder 33)
- Course DEA 445 handouts (Box 1, Folder 34)
- Course DEA 445 assignments, projects, 1977, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 35)
- Project with the Bonnie Prudden School, 1983-1984 (Box 1, Folder 36)
- Research proposals, 1981-1982 (Box 1, Folder 37)
- Description of design competitions, Undated (Box 1, Folder 38)
- Coal mining apparel, 1976-1977 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  Armco Steel Corporation Student Design Program
- Firefighting apparel, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 40)
- Tennessee energy competition, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 41)
- Rehabilitation sleep unit, 1983; Laine, Dalyce (Box 1, Folder 42)
  Rehabilitation Engineering Society of North America Competition
- Description of the National Fire Prevention and Control Administration (NFPCA) publication, Undated (Box 1, Folder 43)
- The Development of Two Protective Apparel Systems for Firefighting, 1978-03-01; Watkins, Susan; Valla. Mary; Rosen, Laurie (Box 1, Folder 44)
  Report submitted to the National Fire Prevention and Control Administration
- Description of course DEA 240, Undated (Box 1, Folder 45)
- Course DEA 240 handouts, 1978-1984 (Box 1, Folder 46)
- Course DEA 240 exams, 1978-1984 (Box 1, Folder 47)
- Course DEA 240 projects, 1973-1980 (Box 1, Folder 48)
- Course DEA 240 lecture, memo about course change, 1983-1985 (Box 1, Folder 49)
- Description of course DEA 146 (TXA 146), Undated (Box 1, Folder 50)
- Course TXA 146 outlines, handouts, 1986-1994 (Box 1, Folder 51)
- Course TXA 146 exhibits, exams, articles, 1988-1998 (Box 1, Folder 52)
- Course TXA 146 final exams, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 53)
- Course TXA 146 winning questions, 1987-1995 (Box 1, Folder 54)
- Description of course readers and audiotape for course TXA 146, Undated (Box 1, Folder 55)
- Course TXA 146 readers, 1990-1992 (Box 1, Folder 56)
- Cassette tape of first lecture course TXA 146, 1994-01; tr-16021 (Box 1, Folder 57)
- Description of course TXA 446, Undated (Box 1, Folder 58)
- Course TXA 446 outlines, sample problems, 1989-1993 (Box 1, Folder 59)
- Course TXA 446 Association of College Professors of Textiles and Clothing competition, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 60)
- Course TXA 446 Envirogear projects, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 61)
- Course TXA446 IBM project, 1989-1990 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  Includes slides and photos
- Course TXA 446 Moonbase project, 1990-1991 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  Includes slides and contact sheets
- Description of the Olympic Projects, Undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Olympic design project - women's karate uniform, 1991; Sokolowski, Susan; United States Olympic Committee (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Olympic design project - ice hockey protective clothing, 1992; Boorady, Lynn; Merck, Eileen; United States Olympic Committee (Box 2, Folder 5)
  Includes slides and articles
- Olympic design project - gloves for special olympics wheelchair racers, 1992; Friedman, Mara; Sanderell, Maggie; United States Olympic Committee (Box 2, Folder 6)
  Includes slides
- Olympic design project - protective gloves for women field hockey players, 1994; Freidman, Wendy; United States Olympic Committee (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Olympic design project - forefoot inclination device for use in court shoes, 1996; Demarest, Nathan; United States Olympic Committee (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Olympic design project - bobsled protective clothing class project, 1997; United States Bobsled and Skeleton Federation (Box 2, Folder 9)
  Includes photos and fabric samples
- Description of course TXA 438, Undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Course TXA 438 outline, handouts notes, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Harley Davidson project, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Course TXA 438 outline, assignments,handouts, notes, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Thorncroft project, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Description of course TXA 246, Undated (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Course TXA 246 outlines, notes, exercises, assignments, Spring (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Course TXA 246 course statement, assignments problems, reader, 1996-1997 (Box 2, Folder 17)
- Description of graduate studies in apparel design, Undated (Box 2, Folder 18)
- Graduate studies brochure, memo, 1989-1995 (Box 2, Folder 19)
- Course TXA 635 letter, notices, course material, 1990-1995 (Box 2, Folder 20)
- Lenora (Lee) Langan article and letter, 1983-1987; Langan, Lenora (Box 2, Folder 21)
- 1987-1990 (Box 2, Folder 22)
- Articles pertaining to Langan's thesis that mens' collars being too tight affects vision, 1987-1988 (Box 2, Folder 23)
- Correspondence from readers pertaining to Langan's thesis, 1987-1990 (Box 2, Folder 24)
- Letters from professors regarding statistics used in Langan's thesis, 1987-1990 (Box 2, Folder 25)
- Proposal for a MPS program in apparel design, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 26)
- Recruitment of undergraduate students, Undated (Box 2, Folder 27)
- Student recruitment plans, flyers, script for slide show, notes, 1987-1996 (Box 2, Folder 28)
- Alumni articles, profiles, letters, 1983-2007 (Box 2, Folder 29)
- Curriculum development memos, articles, notes, reports, 1972-1996 (Box 2, Folder 30)
- Cooperative extension text, Undated (Box 2, Folder 31)
- Clothes for kids report and transcripts of show, 1971; Roland, Cecelia (Box 2, Folder 32)
- Actionware bulletins, scripts, brochures, 1984-1986 (Box 2, Folder 33)
- Sports equipment pamphlets, script, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 34)
- Pesticide protection proposal, report, agenda, 1988-1990 (Box 2, Folder 35)
- Speeches on the intro to functional clothing (Box 2, Folder 36)
- Speech on teaching functional clothing, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 37)
- Speeches on keeping warm in winter cities, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 38)
- Speech on the process of design, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  Given at the annual meeting of the Association of College Professor of Textiles and Clothing
- Speech on designing movement into protective apparel, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  Given at the Industrial Fabrics Association International Conference
- Speech on functional clothing design, 1995-1999 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  Given at the Hospital for Special Surgery
- Speeches given at wheelchair seminars, 1991, 2008 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  Includes programs, handouts, fabric samples
- Speech on the function of creativity, 1999 (Box 2, Folder 43)
- Speech on clothing, the portable environment, 2000 (Box 2, Folder 44)
  Given at Motorola
- List of publications, Undated (Box 2, Folder 45)
- Publications, 1974-1984; Watkins, Susan (Box 2, Folder 46)
- Publications, 1986-2016; Watkins, Susan (Box 2, Folder 47)
- List of encyclopedia entries, Undated (Box 2, Folder 48)
- Encyclopedia entries, 2003-2004; Watkins, Susan (Box 2, Folder 49)
- Sabbaticals, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 50)
- Instructor's manual "Teaching Functional Apparel Design", 2016 (Box 2, Folder 51)
- Vita and honors, 1999-2016 (Box 2, Folder 52)
- Personal statements, 1976-1997 (Box 2, Folder 53)